hi i'm ram gopal from
presentationprocess.com
are you new to powerpoint are you
overwhelmed by
all these tools and buttons in the
software do you need to create your
powerpoint slides in the next one hour
but you don't know how
you have come to the right place
powerpoint is a sophisticated program
with tons of tools
but you don't need to know all of those
tools and functionality to create your
next presentation
you just need to know five percent of
powerpoint to create
an impactful presentation in this video
i'll teach you that five percent
so you can create your next presentation
without any trouble
so let us jump right in and learn
powerpoint
by the way for your convenience we have
added chapters to this
video you just need to place your cursor
along the timeline of this youtube video
to find
exactly what you want to learn alright
now the first question
how do you open powerpoint it's fairly
simple
you go to the bottom left corner of your
screen and click on the start button
and then start typing powerpoint even
before you can finish
typing the entire word you will get this
option for powerpoint app
you click on that option and powerpoint
opens up
by the way i am using microsoft 365 for
this video
but what i am going to teach you will
apply even if you have
powerpoint 2007 version now as soon as
you open powerpoint you will get a
screen like this or
you will get a screen like this for a
new presentation
no matter which version of powerpoint
you use you will have three options here
one is the option to start a blank
presentation
second is the option to choose your
design with the design
themes and third the option to choose
your templates
first let me talk about the templates
let us say you want to make
a business pitch presentation you go to
the option here
and say business pitch
and then hit enter and see what
powerpoint comes up with
as you can see powerpoint gives you a
few options if you like any particular
option like say this one
you click on it and that will open up
this dialog box
here you can read the description and if
you like it you hit create
that downloads the template for you you
just need to replace the sample text
with your own text
and your presentation gets ready even if
the content is not
an exact match for your needs you can
always tweak the content to create your
presentations
i firmly believe that using templates is
always
a big time saver let me close this if
your presentation is not one of the
standard types for which you can pick up
a template and modify
you have two options one is to click on
the blank presentation
or the second which is to click on one
of these design themes
that allows you to start with an
interesting looking slide deck
for this tutorial i am going to start
with a simple
blank presentation now that we have
opened up powerpoint
i'll do two things immediately the first
thing i'll do
is to pin this program onto the taskbar
now what do i mean by that
the next time you want to start the
program you don't really have to go here
type powerpoint and then open the app
all you need to do
is to go down to this bar called as the
task bar
right click on the powerpoint icon and
you have this option called
pin to taskbar you click on it now
powerpoint rests on the taskbar so the
next time you want to open it
you just need to click on this and
powerpoint opens up
now with that out of the way the next
thing i will do is to save the
presentation
i've seen so many cases where the
presenter has done so much work on
creating a presentation
and leaves it unsaved and accidentally
closes the file
to lose all the work i don't want you to
suffer from that
so develop the habit of saving your
presentation
right off the gate so how do you save
the presentation
you take your cursor to the top left
corner and click on
file and then click on this option
called
save as and then choose the location
where you want to save your presentation
in this case i want to save it on the
desktop so i'm going to click on
that option give this a memorable name
i'm going to call this powerpoint basics
and you can see that the file type is
dot pptx
that is exactly the format we want you
just hit
save now when i go to the taskbar right
click and go to
show the desktop option i can see my
presentation here called powerpoint
basics
so the next time i want to open and
access the file i just need to double
click on the icon
and that opens up that specific file
excellent
the second task is done now the third
task
now that you have come this far it is
important for you to know a few
terminologies
that will allow you to search for
information from either the help
or from google and you will be able to
make sense of the instructions
so let us learn the basic terminology of
powerpoint
the large panel that you see here on
your screen is called as
the slide area then the panel that you
see
on the left is called as the thumbnail
area
then the most important area on your
screen is
this area called as powerpoint ribbon
the ribbon is made of a collection of
tabs that look like this
you click a tab to access a collection
of tools
called as group so to summarize
powerpoint has a number of tools the
tools related to a specific task
are clubbed together as a group and a
collection of groups
is called a tab and a collection of tab
is found in a ribbon
the strip that you see at the bottom
which has a few commands is called as
the status bar
excellent that is as much terminology
that you need to know
the next thing i'm going to do is to
start creating the slide
powerpoint has made it extremely easy
for a beginner to start creating the
slides
you just need to do what powerpoint says
here it says click to add title
so i'm going to click on it and i'm
going to write the title of this
presentation
in this case it will be called
powerpoint basics
now i can see that i have made some
mistake here i can always right click on
this and click on the right option
just as it works with any of the other
software programs that you are familiar
with
i can click on this to add subtitle
maybe i can write my name here
this is the name of the presenter now
i've got my first slide ready
but then the slide looks so plain that
you don't want to present the slide to
anyone
so let us see how we can quickly improve
the design
of this slide all you need to do for
that is
go to this tab here called as design and
here you have the option called
themes themes allow you to add
professional design to your slides
quickly
now observe what happens when i take my
cursor over these design theme options
let me place my cursor here you can
instantly see the result in this live
preview
as i move my cursor to the next option
you can see the design
applied instantaneously now you're not
restricted only to these options
you can click on the drop down menu here
and that opens up even more options for
you to add
design to your slides if you like any
particular option like say
this one you can click on it and
instantly your slide looks
far more professional once you select a
design theme
you will see these options called as
variants
these are the variations of the design
theme you chose
for example instead of this orange color
if you want blue color you can choose
this
green color you can choose or purple
color you can choose
let me choose this blue color and i'm
well on my way to impress my audience
with my slide deck next i want to add a
new slide to write my content
how do i do that i can go to the
thumbnail view
click on that and hit enter and i have
my new slide available
if you want a more traditional way you
can go to the home tab
and here you have the option called new
slide now that brings me to the next
option i want you to notice here you can
see in certain buttons
you have the icon available and you have
the drop down menu
available related to that icon when you
click on that option
when you see here for new slide we have
this drop down menu available
you can choose any of these layouts for
your next slide
so whenever you choose a tool see if
that tool has
the small downward arrow available next
to it
if it has then you can click on that
option and you will have the drop down
menu
available by the way you can expand
certain groups to find
more options for example let me click on
this
and you can see in this group we have
this arrow available
when i click on that option you can see
that we have these floating dialog boxes
open up
that give us even more options now let
us not get confused with all those
options right now
all i want you to remember is whenever
you choose a tool always try to see if
you can expand the options
so you can choose the exact tool that
you want
excellent now let us come back to
creating our slides
here i want to write the topics that i
am going to discuss
in this presentation so i am going to
click on the title
let us say topics and then i'm going to
add my options here
the first option is i'm going to talk
about the home tab
hit enter and then i'm going to talk
about
the design tab hit enter and i'm going
to talk about
animations hit enter and i'm going to
talk about
transitions so these are the topics that
i'm going to discuss
in this presentation now what you've
done is you've created one of the
classic slide types
in any presentation you've created a
bullet point slide
a typical bullet point slide lists items
like this
but then the problem is these bullet
point slides are usually quite boring
is there a way you can make your slides
look lot more appealing than these
bullet point slides
yes you can let me show you how we have
a beautiful option
in powerpoint called as smartart
diagrams
let me show you how easy it is for you
to convert this boring looking slide
into
a visual slide you select all these
bullet points by clicking
and dragging your cursor across then
right click
and go to the option called convert to
smartart
and here you can see that we have a
whole bunch of options available
let me choose the first one now my slide
already looks a lot better another way
for you to visualize your slides
is to insert pictures let me show you
how that is done
let me hit enter by going to the
thumbnail view
let us write types of roots which
happens to be the title
now the next thing i want to get rid of
is this placeholder
so i'm going to change the layout i can
right click on
any blank area of the slide go to
this option called layout and i can
choose a different layout
now we are on this title and content
layout
i can have this option called title only
and now i have the space available for
me to visualize my information
the first option we have is apples so i
need to
insert the picture of apples how do you
do that
you go to the tab here called insert and
here we have the option called
pictures you click on the drop down menu
as i told you before
and you can choose to insert pictures
from any of these three options
one is this device that is if you have
already downloaded the picture of apples
then you can click on this option if you
have office 365 subscription you have
this option called stock images
if you are on an earlier version of
powerpoint you will have this option
called online pictures
you click on online pictures here in the
dialog box that opens up
you can search for what you want in this
case i want to search for apples
let me write that and hit enter and bing
searches for
the various images you can use on your
slides i like this
option so i'm going to click on that and
let me say insert
now i will have the picture of apples on
my slide
i can click on this picture hold the
shift button
down as i click and drag one of these
handles
in the corner and i can resize the image
and i can place it over here now i need
to label this
so let me go to insert again and you
will find
this option here called as text box you
click on that
and then you click on the slide and you
will get the text box option
you start typing your label in this case
it is apples
you select that now you go to the option
here called font
and if you want to change the font type
you can click on the drop down menu here
and you can choose any of these options
i am quite okay with the current font
next if you want to increase the size of
this label you can use
this option here where a is written in a
bigger font
let me click on that a couple of times
now as i click on this you can see that
the font size increases
and it reflects here on the slide let me
now place this over here
and i have my label written for my first
picture
let me do that again very quickly i want
to insert the picture of
oranges which happens to be the next
option so let me go to the slide
go to insert go to pictures go to online
pictures
and let me search for oranges
hit enter and i have various pictures of
oranges available
i like this one you insert you select
the picture
hold the shift button down click and
drag from the corner
so you can resize it nicely and then
place it right next to the previous one
now if i want to save some time i can
copy this text box
by selecting the text box right clicking
and
choosing this option called copy then
right click on the slide
and choose this option called paste and
now i can place this label over here
right
under the next picture and i can call
this oranges
and now i have my second picture labeled
now take a look at how
this slide looks compared to the earlier
one and that is the reason why it is
always preferable
to add pictures and visuals to make your
slides come to life
now to summarize whatever we have learnt
so far we learned how to open up
powerpoint
we learnt how to save it we learnt about
the terminology
we learned how to create a slide by
clicking and writing our text
we learnt how to insert a new slide we
learned how to convert the basic bullet
point into
a simple diagram we also learned how to
visualize our information
by inserting pictures and the
corresponding labels
the next thing you want to know is how
to present your slides
to present your slides you need to
choose an option called
slideshow for that you need to take your
cursor down to the status bar
and you will see these icons available
here let us quickly understand
what these icons represent the one that
you see here which is clicked by default
is called as the normal view
the option next to it is called as slide
sorter view
when you click on it you can see all the
slides in one glance
the one that you see right next to it is
called as the reading view
i don't usually use it much to come out
of this view you can hit
escape the option that we would use to
present our slide is
this one called as slideshow you select
your first slide
and then you click on this option called
slideshow
and you would be able to present your
slides this is our first slide
to advance to the next slide you can
choose any of the options
like you can hit your enter button on
the keyboard
or you can hit your space bar or you can
use
up and down arrow keys on your keyboard
or you can hit page up and page down on
your keyboard
whatever is convenient to you you can
use let me use the simplest option which
is
to hit enter that takes me to the next
slide
to go back to the previous slide i can
hit page up
and that takes me to one slide back so
let me hit enter here is the second
slide
the next slide and the next slide now
you know how to create a basic bullet
point slide
you know how to convert that into a
simple diagram using smartart
you also know how to visualize your
slide using pictures
and the labels at this point you know
more about powerpoint
than most people now to come out of the
slideshow you hit
escape now to go to a specific slide you
double click on the slide
and that takes you to the normal view
now let us take our skill
to the next level we are going to add
simple animation to our slides
so that we can hold the audience's
attention here on this slide
we have four elements that is two
pictures
and two texts so let us add a simple
animation
to reveal one item at a time to add
all you need to do is to click on the
object that you want to animate
go to the animations tab then you use
a simple animation called fade animation
as a beginner i don't want you to use
any of these other options that can be
quite exciting just stick with
the basic simple fade animation so we
have got our first animation in place
right after showing the picture we are
going to show the label
so let me click on the second object i
want to animate
and hit fade then i click on the next
object
and hit fade then the next object and
then hit fade
and then when i go to slideshow by going
to this option here
you can see that i can present these
objects on a click
on the first click i show the picture of
apples
and then on the next click i show the
corresponding label
then on the next click i show the
picture of oranges
then the corresponding labels can you
see here you can present your
information at your own pace
and you can hold the audience's
attention with simple animation
as i said earlier if you want to come
out of the slideshow mode
you hit the escape button on your
keyboard now as the last step
to add polish to our slide deck we are
going to add
transitions so the movement from one
slide to the next
happens a bit more dramatically so let
us go to the first slide
then go to the transitions tab then
choose from any of these
transition options a simple transition
that works well
in any business setup is wipe transition
you can click on that option you can see
that this is the preview of the wipe
transition
once you select the transition you go to
this option here called
apply to all that applies the transition
to all the slides in your deck
so there is consistency in the way the
slides move
now with the first slide selected let us
go to slideshow
and here we have the first slide shown
now with a click
see how the second slide is shown with a
nice transition
by just adding a simple transition you
can add
so much professionalism in the way your
slide deck looks and feels
that's it now with this much knowledge
you can create your basic slide deck
and impress your audience always
remember to go to file
and keep hitting the save option so that
you can save your work
if at any point you feel you need to up
your powerpoint game
and get a strong foundation in the
program then i highly recommend that you
join our
complete powerpoint foundation course
this is a 13 and a half
hour course with step by step video
tutorials that teach you
all that you need to know about
powerpoint foundation
the course is priced affordably and you
get lifetime access to this program with
one time payment
the link to this course is available in
the description box below the video
you click on the link and check out more
details about this program
and take your powerpoint skills to the
next level finally
if you want to join our 25 creative
ideas free powerpoint mini training
you can click on the link here to watch
our latest video on powerpoint in
presentation process channel you can
click on the link here
if you like this video please give this
video a like
share it with your friends and hit the
subscribe button to enjoy more such
videos
thanks a lot for watching this video
i'll see you in the next one